so the present need you removed for you
what is it over
designed to hide yeah it's an it's not
too much thinking dollar yeah that's for
you Buddhist opaque so various ways of
describing it so when you describe you
know that how does that feel that same
thing you're describing feels unpleasant
its unpleasant and what shape does it
have the same thing you're describing it
feels unpleasantly cloud like a bean use
pressure is loud yes so what do you
think then you will describe it now
let's what do I think
hey what are you describing now by this
description or description for feeling
description through Heights being to see
an image and what is that image and what
does that even stand for what is your
mood stand
what is presently enduring feeling and
presently during perception what are
they determine your mind to describe in
your mindless yeah there's no money
don't image of the mind
yeah mind is the shape of the moon
that's why in such a pattern elated mind
depressed mind of the mind heavy mind
light mind whatever any absolutely we
can add to it because that's the extent
of its appearance it's that kind of a
certain shape that being felt of a
certain mood in their general level so
what's the problem there why in anybody
knows it so why am I not another hand
then yet if I'm not another hand yet if
you're seeing the mind correctly
partnership resolving the content of the
mind so it's not like something you're
missing out but it's in your attitude
toward your own mind the assumptions you
have towards the own presently enduring
mind not the mind that yesterday -
tomorrow this mind that we just
described right here right now so
present enduring mind of an unpleasant
state and I'm present mood is there a
problem anywhere is the problem if there
is where is it because not understanding
where the problem is this why you're not
still completely free from suffering
it's not because you haven't waited long
enough for that's why some people need
afford an orbit half a night one night
some given either three nights seven
nights four nights six months Sonja's
whatever
so there is a presently kneeling shape
of the mind the mood basically that's
what mine is pretty much that's felt
disagreeably is there a problem with
that he's I don't
I don't
what do you think
I have to look at what what is the what
it's at least for me missed hurting me
yeah anything anything that you would
deem needs fixing that's what definition
on how it is okay so the problem is
does it need fixing
yeah there is a I think busy there's an
attitude that it shouldn't is that's not
a good thing to have dullness but Paik
right right am i right
that's not the optimal thing yeah so
what is the optimum exactly now now that
you kind of shed light onto that
attitude then you ask okay but do I know
what the optimum state is why is this
not optimal state you know what color
what what is the optimum and also isn't
that optimal state an idea that can't
escape yes very much
sure that I'm just describing like would
you be able to even ambiguously have a
notion of an optimal state if this an
optimal state is under enduring so here
you are completely you seriously have an
assumption in regard to quite clear
clearly describe present enduring state
of mind yet you have ambiguous
assumption that something must be done
but you don't quite know what where to
what an extent you just feels that way
so why would you think that is a case
then why would you hold such an
assumption because another one literal
thing so the only reason the only reason
you're thinking that this is not optimum
it's because you want to get rid of it
and ironically it's because of you want
to get rid of it that's where things are
not optimal that's why you're gonna tell
you so things are not optimal because
the mind is in a dark state ascetic
gotama Souter says he knows his mind as
doubt her mind as a later man as a
weight in mind there is neither optimal
or not optimal that just state of mind
so you could see that then he knows down
- dull mind means he knows this what we
just clarified so you not you caring
assumption that this is not optimal
because basically on the on the
emotional level you you're still
resisting that this pleasure means you
don't know the mind to that extent and
that's why you're finding it on optimal
that's why want to replace it with a
more optimal state it's like complaining
the weather's the whether it should be
sunny buddies can yeah but that's like
that's bit too far removed what you
described was quite accurate and when
I'm pointing out is now even more I
could I don't talk about that so yes a
view oh it's just a mood and stuff but
you want to see that even even the
slightest attitude towards present
enduring mind first you recognize that
it shouldn't be that is present in your
mind is not there what you pointed out
there already kind of rounds out the
image as a whole as opposed to you just
blindly trying to replace it and then
you get to reveal that the only reason
this is deemed an optimal is because you
don't want it and the reason why it is
truly not optimal is because you don't
want it it was because of what it is
doesn't doesn't listen that based on the
sub there's doesn't matter what is based on
there's doesn't matter what is based on
what I was just thinking like you need
to say that I don't want this is again
this assumptions it's something outside
of this that can that can change it that
can yeah but again like see them but I'm
trying is trying to stay on the level of
you just removing the attitude without
needing to overly explain okay but you
are having at it should fall which would
be accurate but he's gonna start leaning
on the side of theory okay so the
present enduring mind it's still
presently enduring is regarded is a nun
optimal also presently enduring within
that doesn't matter how I came about to
walking about you just want to realize
that that attitude of this is not
optional is White's are loved not their
attitude is injured of course of course
yeah so you said like you sound trading
to get rid of yeah okay you know that as
you stop craving to get rid of the pain
you basically start including it with an
attitude of also this is not optimal is
within the present enduring state of one
such a such mood in such a such mind
that then you will stop not wanting
because you are accepting it on the
right level the only reason you're not
wanting it because you don't know that
that's what the problem is and to set up
an eyes he knows the mind is such as
such and that's why it's the right
mindfulness so you're gonna probably
answer is why you shouldn't want it you
just want to realize that you wanting or
not wanting of it in treacherous and is
negligent gratuity then you maintain
that's why the problem is there so if I
don't want the state of mind that I
don't want this anger hmm you're not
saying recognize it and they didn't
recognize it
where did you go to one yeah it's not a
problem anymore once you recognize no no
that's not quite what I'm saying because
see you recognize your mind but you
haven't recognized your attitude
to mine as this description started you
raccoon as the mind clearly you describe
how it feels and stuff I even asked you
by the attitude is there a problem you
described that but you haven't
recognized that there was the problem
you thought the man was the problem you
thought the mind was an optimal state so
you say to somebody just accept anger it
will help them initially to that extent
but you need to you need to accept more
than that then just accept the a reason
anger you need to accept the lack of
knowledge through which you can develop
the knowledge where the actual anger is
and it's not in the mind it's in your
lack of knowledge of the mind which is
not to be found anywhere else apart from
the mind but it's not the mind like I
said whether said the nature of Perdana
it's not the fiber griots but it cannot
be found at us apart from the five
ingredients and that's why yeah those
genetic instructions just be here now
don't judge things and just accept
whatever comes your way does offer a
relief to people cuz offers like a
blanket acceptance and it works when you
are rejecting things but it doesn't work
when you are overly accepting them your
blanket acceptance of war will accept
the things doesn't work it just makes it
worse that's what these genetic views are
that's what these genetic views are
still the wrong wheels but they get
something right sometimes accidentally
and you don't rely on the accident so
it's knowing the state of the mind as
you clearly did as you described knowing
how it's present if being felt knows how
to presently being perceived and then
basically peripheral to that revealing
your own attitudes towards it such as
any or this is inadequate great there
you go see unless you cloudy for the
mind you wouldn't have said all this is
nobody okay the man said okay so what's
the problem then
okay perhaps if I didn't question you in
that direction you would have not maybe
arrived at you right away but the point
is you did and then okay so the problem
is feels an adequate and now that brings
light to that okay why why why do i why
do i they got the present enduring state
of - you nothing inadequate for what
inadequate why know yet the attitude is
there that's exactly the point you will
press why why and you will see that the
only reason why it's because I haven't
been thinking why in regards to this
particular attitude
I haven't been thinking why am I
regarding this is an inequity
which is why I've been regarding it as
inadequate because I I didn't know it
that's it and it's literally uprooting
the ignorance uprooting things that
you've been ignoring him because of
which they were there that's it but not
the mind you know not routing the mind
the mind doesn't disappear but uprooting
those things that shouldn't have been
there in the first place like okay Don
is not part of the agreeance you come
measure degrades and measure up or down
in regard to it is just not in them
can it doesn't manifest in like minutes
between doesn't many physicians always
peripheral it's always the attitude of
ignoring what manifests and you can then
have the units manifest in front of you
and then choose to stop denoting it
because you believe knowing that suits
to the level of the attitude attitude
that can only be understood through you
digging up in that direction and
revealing oh this is a present in your
mind this is a president eerie feeling
to understand it well to an extent okay
what defines an extent to my
understanding why do I say understand a
little bit what little bit I do
understand what now I'm aware they
didn't use I'm aware of its
characteristics its manifestation so I'm
great so why am I not another hand in
yet that's a good question or maybe oh
that's a good question or maybe oh
because it's kind of still not adequate
not I could have adequate for what then
you lose you have no idea what is not
adequate for you just kept assuming cuz
that's how you started you started by
knowing I'm not in lights and I want to
be enlightened and then you've been
doing the practice and solid brought you
closer to it but but you never get
enlightened until you approved you're
wrong ideas of what enlightenment is
you'll never find adequate optimal
things until you approach your ideas of
this is an optimal which is the reason
why things are not often
no because they were not optimally
themself because you just kept regarding
him so
that's what we spoke before like an
litem is not at the end of some great
pursuit the element of Nibbana the
element of dispassion removal of our
version the illusion distraction
ignorance is too close to people's point
of view that's why it's invisible it's
not because it's hidden in some
mysterious cave or something now it's
just so close that you can't see it your
threshold of seeing starts wait on line
and that threshold seeing is determined
by the threshold of your assumptions you
see like unless now now you clarified
what at least hinted at certain
increased clarity in regard to the
presently during mood of any kind and
your attitude exhibited to vote it
optimal an optimal what criteria do I
have for judging this but until you
thought about it that's it any time you
felt in a heavy hazy ambiguous mood your
attitude entirely was Childre an optimal
don't be dumb
you don't go closer to it because it's
not optimal so you just sort of go about
your day enduring until it changes and
something being this more optimal comes
yet optimal and optimal was your
attitude wasn't in those things wasn't
in the state of the mind so for as long
as you're alive as long as their father
idiots as long as it is mine enduring
having like manifested the enduring
things are more than optimal for full
understanding
the only true on optimal state is when
you're dead okay now things are not
optimal
because there can be no discernable
image yeah because you might end up in a
worse place off where you won't be able
to think or replace even more
pleasurable where you won't be able to
think
and as you yourself they wield quite
accurately the only reason it's not
optimal is because it displeases you
because it's felt unpleasantly and the
reason why a person is not in Ireland is
because he still has craving in the
guard for how he feels
so the present enduring mood that's
uncomfortable that's the extent and
that's not an issue nothing within that
can be an issue but it seriously still
holding on to the attitude of I have a
right to not want disagreeable and
because of that the entire experience in
its content is Dimas non-optimal because
if I makes you feel because of what it
is
so you stopped maintaining your rights
to the in regard to how you feel
can any perception bother you then it
doesn't matter how it's felt and then
anything that manifests to you be
optimal or an optimal would have even
conceivable but you're not feeling it
anymore at all
that's just just a fee hey it's true
yeah it's just manifest the thing they
didn't use says it file aggregates
manifesting audience enduring have
manifested that's it
so the practice is really just reminding
yourself of that direction that you
obviously already know that so it's not
enough to get the sense of direction
once the right direction
yeah Johnny cuz yeah you don't you don't
know what things are gratuitous Lee
there because if you were to know them
they wouldn't be there you're to lose
them so dealt with a knife is to be the
so dealt with a knife is to be the
center cutting keep digging captain's
splitting cutting not for the sake of
theoretical scholastic analysis but for
the sake of clarity yeah so I suppose
this is the right analysis you're not
analyzing things in a theoretical sense
but in actually present in using sense
that's what I like to call it an
analysis like cutting this section yeah
but dissecting nothing in terms of like
I saw with this look this although when
you put it in words is it gonna sound
like that if you don't understand any
other way of this second ear but we just
detected it's more through the present
enduring feeling with a sector the
present enduring attitude in regards to
that feeling which we then decided
further that that's where the problem is
not as originally assumed on the level
of the mind it's not so much about
scratching things apartment looking at
things within things within things
yeah that we do not dig through the same
hole further and further far as the
buddha said so just once you once you
see where from oh yeah if you see the
actual about the problem see you you you
thought firstly the problem was the mind
is not not optimal but then through
contemplating it together became clear
that it's your attitude in regard to
mind where the problem is and that an
optimal mine attitude was rooted in that
not in the mind so seeing where the
problem is actually routed correctly and
does the problem while not seeing it
once you mind to see it a few more times
because it's a habit of regarding things
rather I think the mind which is dull is
the problem yes sir that's so you
startled for that yeah you still have a
problem exist why is this foot problem
because that's why I didn't ask you that
I didn't ask you do you have a problem I
asked you what is your present in your
mood because that is the container of
whether there is a problem or not
there is a container of whether it's an
otter suitable to Jeana or it's a
completely fully enlighten our hands
skilled in all genres
the mind is there in doing so that's the
container so what is that you describe
it then I started asking about the
problems but yeah oh is that a problem
we would have been talking about your
mind and wouldn't be talking about a
problem that you regard to be within
your mind we'll be talking about the
idea of the problem an idea of the
practice present enduring mind how is it
felt how is it perceived is there a problem
how is it perceived is there a problem
in it if not are you rolling elephant
oh no no so where is the problem so
there must be a problem there is a world
probably doesn't seem optimal okay great
so you have an attitude that's also real
and during there that's why it's
important to it not keep trying to deny
things that's wrong is wrong from get
rid of this because they're not denying
the present enduring mood to allow me to
endure through not denying the present
enduring attitude towards your mood
allowing it to endure you get to
understand that the problem is there
because you are putting it there not
because it was rooted in the mind but if
you haven't even allowed your present
enduring mood to endure if you were too
busy observing it or trying to monitor
it in the level of sensations or ideas
you would have seen any of this
so what you what removes the problem is
the descent body moves our problem is is
not being ignorant of the true nature of
the problem not miss concealing the
nature of the problem so if there is
still a problem means I haven't asserted
to nature yeah exactly and whether you
want that there is still a problem ask
yourself I am a completely fully
unshakably free from suffering the
answer's no means here is a problem so
there's no it's not about to placings
yeah yeah I do a technique
yeah it's thoughts I make my mind sunny
and bright too
it means you don't know where the
problem is you blame the problem on the
state of the mind for which you're not
saying the rising so you blame basically
problem of your kupatana of your
assumptions you put it in the aggregate
so he's the aggregates problem owner
change the shape of the aggregates
that's why I changed my problem that's
why I deal with it
you want to change things too so that it
feels good
pretty much this will boil down to note
that not that a person is aware of that
attitude something is wrong
applied technique to get to get it right
oh good and the definition of right is
it feels pleasing to me but I guess it's
not so the only dark mean now if you
can't see that the problem is in know
the things but they don't know what I
view let's be said in previous talks you
can practice writing without knowing
what the practice is and all over the
practices is where the writing begins so
the idea that oh I know I don't have a
right view and I also know what I
practice easily process anyway because I
can't practice yeah well that's the
process and you say can I Drive here
yeah and then practice is that practice
right yeah so I can do it oh so what do
i do then will you get a review so what
they do together I do
I'll stop maintaining the wrong views I
just thought maintaining the wrong views
but learning what the right view is how
to learn but drivers were thinking about
and writing what could be by
understanding the nature of it so that's
the closest to the method you can get
hmm trying to understand it's the closer to
trying to understand it's the closer to
the truth but to what you can do in
order to understand but oh well not try
to question the nature of the right view
of the wrong view and try to understand
it no I'll just do this yeah how'd you
do what Rajan tells me is easy no yeah
yeah okay that's it cuz I have faith you
can't hold the faith you want did you
did you
we've been told that craving mr. Fung
yeah of course you need to be told where
to get other ones yeah you weren't told
that that's where the two factors for
realizing that you are parents of
another as in or another who knows so we
and then you rightly attending to it you
see the mind let's see the attitude yeah
see like we see the mind see unless you
start questioning say you started
completely first time you hear this I
need to see my mind you have some idea
what that mind is but your practice is
not about now figuring out what your
idea is the practice is undoing that
idea because your starting point of an
analyte of mine is the point of the
wrong view in regard to whatever you
choose to attend so I have the idea what
the - that's fine
but I shouldn't be building my practice
on the idea of the mind that I have my
practice should be undoing the idea of
the mind that I have until I arrive at
the right idea and I know it's the right
idea because I'll be unable to suffer
amid suffering I would need to protect
it defend it or get all upset when I
come across supposing view that's
nothing if you get emotionally
threatened by hearing an opposing view
that should tell you something about
your own views why would you impose an
existential threat to you a difference
of opinion yeah does me you accept it by
the way you said the utterance questions
of innova para para ago sir para can
noticed in the party para can mean
another though you said like a there has
to be somebody who has the right view
but para can also mean outside and
beyond yeah you should dislike it's like
inside of this perspective exactly
so anything whether it's a it's a
written word uttered word but he
actually get to talk to somebody who
understands or not yeah maybe you come
across it by the point is he has to be
from outside of your point of view has
to be outside from your point of view
not to any random thing outside of but
the right thing outside and the point of
view because you're fully enclosed
within the attitude of ignorant
you can't just choose to not be ignorant
or like oh I choose to not not cling to
this I choose to not get all up a ton
about this it's not a method of choice
if that's a matter of choice literally
all you need to do is choose to become
another hand yeah it doesn't work that
way doesn't it doesn't matter take the
power of your conviction
so knowing in order for you to them when
I asked you how what is the present
think what are the characters were
present enduring mood as it felt has it
as high as this even that order they
require you to have to other didn't know
what your mind is to that extent which
means you already have undone a lot of
wrong assumptions of what the mind is if
I ask you 15 years ago what is your mind
how are you feeling right now do you
think you would give me a remotely
similar answer no but for most people
getting their own thoughts don't feel
like they don't even exist they're not
real big zip but they're not real let
alone then which is peripheral to the
thoughts which is the State of Mind you
we just abstract shapes and ideas and
you have no concept how to relate to it
and it doesn't matter what they are in
the content whether they're shapes or
ideals what matches your attitude
towards it that's to the vinegar of mind
toward his own mind is that she doesn't
see it as in it's not real and it's
exactly what people deem real things to
be only things that come to your senses
because that's how far removed they are
from recognizing their own mind as a
real thing which is a real thing would
you be able to tell me the shape of your
mood if the shape wasn't there would you
be able to create the shape out of
nothingness if he wasn't given as an
option to be created that see was there
and most people wouldn't even regard
that as a real thing although they'll be
talking about it acting out of it at the
same time the regard is no real no real
means not worth attending they're not
worth engine it means not worth dealing
with so I'm just doing instead of a so
I'll just see how my belly feels when I
breathe I'll just constraint the tip of
my nostrils what is that sense of sense
of sense of itself that's where the
reality is
the closer I look at the sense objects
the closer to the reality I am the
closer to the assumed
reality you are which is the reality of
your own assumption so in other words
your own assumption your own wrong views
grow
the attitude is for or against that mind
you know for you to discern your
attitude towards the mind you need to
listen the mind
no to the sender mind first you need to
allow it to endure in whatever state
it's in during stop trying to habitually
interfere later change it for something
being more optimal then you get to
reveal your attitude towards it which is
overly accepting overly denying either
way I'm not saying it we were not seeing
it for against turns turning away from
setting away from it yeah I don't wanna
think about it but all of those
attitudes that's the irony of it can
only be exhibited within the present in
your mind so that's why greed aversion
distraction can never really make any
difference to the aggregates cannot like
you cannot really escape them you cannot
really turn away from them you cannot
really get to them closer if you want
them present they're up there all that
greed hatred division are kind of all
about trying to deny or get away from or
will get more off yeah as you you are
separate from that you can get more of
it for you
so learning how to live among mine clean
you develop that method that you had to
choose for but I do that all of that can
only be able to on the basis of
presently enduring mind yeah did you
would obviously they're not seeing or
not discerning you have a sense of it
but you know discerning it which is why
you're trying to get rid of it or trying
to get more of it or trying to override
immediately to what you think it should
be as in more of it or less of it or
none of it all of those things are
possible only because it is there and
they're all within it yeah it comes
first and stays first yeah no matter how
much they are the same control since
it's one yeah the old there's a boot
let's say the old doesn't disappear when
you start engaging with its parts no the
only reason you can engage with its
parts is because the old is still there
the old being defined you said that they
had to choose unnecessary yeah it's you
did you choose yeah Greedo executors
greece an Earthship a version is an edge
to these two tutors distractions are
nice you'd agree to this
it's honestly because why because you
can't be there in the first place makes
no difference to the aggregates in the
first place the only reason no
difference yeah no knowing that it makes no
yeah no knowing that it makes no
difference that's why you keep trying to
make a difference which is the whole
resistance of samsara so what is the
attitude is a relinquishment of all
attitudes mean that's the earth just say
region so the attitude is indifference
the attitude of and she's being honest a
well the extinguishing of attitude you
can but it's the only one right actually
but it's the only one right actually
also known as nirvana
so the bond is also a Dhamma like other
things like other things that you
exhibit but it's the only Dhamma not
determined by anything any any basically
wrong assumption good could you say a
difference equanimity chocolate that's
how it's felt just looking on impecca
yes relinquish you of all attitudes towards
relinquish you of all attitudes towards
the fiving age is the attitudes that's
felt economist Lee which means something
felt so by all means develop that
attitude towards everything is about the
right attitude okay so it will said be
like fire be like earth be like wind
because wind doesn't get bothered by my
white had its pleasant sort of pleasant
things it blows over fire doesn't care
what burns what it burns whether it's
disgusting things or agreeable things
basically develop your attitude that's
gonna go beyond pleases me displeases me
and thus i decide this should be here
shouldn't be here
that's why I accept it that's why I
rejected that's why I neither accepted
nor rejected so develop the utter
indifferent attitude toward how you feel
it's not towards what you feel because
that's that's the that's the extensive
domain the people can't see everybody
your chaos outside emulating the
attitude economy towards everything
everything that comes my way which kind
of does still imply the problem is in
those things which is why your economist
towards what what I hear say which is
the good start but don't expect that to
result in you briefly is only different
because you wanted to change yes sooner
or later that attitude gonna run out of
its determination and then you will be
bothered by things that come your way
but if your attitude with regard to
whatever it's being felt presently and
there's always something present Infeld
means you're ready to disregard to the
nature of feelings not anymore the
content on that so you have to be
skilled in failing yeah which is me
being skilled in the mind because
there's no
feelings did not vinegar outline
some people practice letting go oh this
upset me I let go this upset me let go
well practice the same let go towards
present enduring feeling not towards
whatever caused that feeling just those
pregnant you feel for as long as it
injures because then people will start
to let go the feeling by the means of
getting rid of the feeling no that's all
I can go the feeling that's you trying
to get rid of the feeling what happens
you're letting go of it means not
interfering with it so don't need to
feel with present theories and feelings
that can be a method another method hmm
not interfering don't feel with
presently didn't feel alive turned it
yeah yeah but see but that that can
appear interference I will not interfere
with this okay great
let's ask yourself why yeah why am I not
interfere it is because I don't want it
there oh so y'all need to feel him with
it through your non interference oh it
could be that one no but it's still
closer then you blaming things because
of which you felt they could be
preferable but still it's it's not it's
no close enough it's not accurate but it
can result in in greater accuracy then
because you stopped being concerned with
the objects now with things you seen
hear smell taste touch even thought but
only concerned with what present
enduring feeling and then try to not
interfere which means try not to indulge
it try not to get rid of it or as the
Buddha said don't delight in it don't
welcome it don't don't move still remain
holding yeah don't don't basically creep
on a tacky holding tank
two loads of methods yeah but you got to
use that part